<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A caueat to preuent future iudgements: or, An admonition to all England more specially, to London and other places where the death of plague hath lately beene. By Robert Horn Minister of the Word.</title>
            <author>Horne, Robert, 1565-1640.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1626</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 72 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03693</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13820</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116563</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851779</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851779</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17070</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03693)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17070)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1312:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A caueat to preuent future iudgements: or, An admonition to all England more specially, to London and other places where the death of plague hath lately beene. By Robert Horn Minister of the Word.</title>
                  <author>Horne, Robert, 1565-1640.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G. M[iller] for Philemon Stephens and Christopher Meredith, and are to be sold at their shop at the golden Lyon in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1626.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: An admonition to all England.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Plague --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17070:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17070:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A CAVEAT to preuent future IVDGEMENTS: Or, AN ADMONITION to all ENGLAND; more ſpecially, to LONDON and other places where the death of Plague hath lately beene. (<g ref="char:dtristar">*⁎*</g>)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> ROBERT HORN <hi>Miniſter of the Word.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSAL. 50.22.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Now conſider this, yee that forget God, leſt I teare you in peeces and there be none to deliuer.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>G. M.</hi> for <hi>Philemon Stephens</hi> and <hi>Criſtopher Meredith,</hi> and are to be ſold at their ſhop at the golden Lyon in Pauls Church-yard. 1626.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:17070:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17070:2"/>
            <head>TO THE VVORSHIPFVLL AND REVEREND MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron, Miſtreſſe AGNES DANET of <hi>Weſthope</hi> in <hi>Shropſhire,</hi> Widow; the comforts of this life, and the glorie of the next.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>WORSHIPFVLL M<hi>
                     <hi rend="sup">rs</hi>.</hi> DANET<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Our Obligation vpon Me, binds me, at leaſt, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement. I with my wife, liued with you in houſe twenty yeeres, ſaue ſome few weekes. Moſt of which time, or (ſaue ſome few moneths) the whole of it, I liued Preacher to your Tenants and priuate familie, at a Chappell by; being there ſet and left by that rightly worſhipfull and truly religious old Gentleman, your moſt kinde husband, <hi>IOHN DANET</hi> Eſquire, long ſince with God. The inſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s you receiued that while from me, &amp; before that while of time from faithfull men elſewhere, I doubt not but you remember and will practiſe for your part and time heere. Some teſtimony you lately gaue in your zealous and conſtant obſeruation of thoſe Faſts which were (weekely) commanded for <hi>London</hi> by Royall authority, notwithſtanding your often infirmities and great yeeres: which makes me now, vnder your name, to ſend forth this ſmall Sermon, and to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>title you to it as to your owne by many intereſts. In regard of the Plagues late fearefull increaſe in <hi>London,</hi> and other places about, and further off, there came a commandement from our <hi>Auguſtus</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:17070:3"/>(King <hi>CHARLES</hi>) that all of the Realme, that could, or were fit, ſhould meete together in a publike weekely Fast on Wedneſdaies, to beſeech the Lord by prayer and ſupplications, vntill it ſhould pleaſe him to ſay, as ſometime he ſaid to the deſtroying Angel, with his ſword ouer <hi>Ieruſalem; it is enough, hold now thy hand, 2. Sam. 24.16.</hi> To this, and to vs his Royall Maieſty began in a rare Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent: and ſo, did no more by precept then what he firſt ſealed by pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe in his owne high Perſon. The Plague was great: and ſo we faſted, and beſought our God for it: and he was entreated of vs, <hi>Ezra</hi> 8.23. vpon the ſucceſſe (wonderfull in our eares, moſt ſtrange in <hi>Londons</hi> eyes) his Maieſty, hath ſince publiſhed his Royall pleaſure for publike thankes to God, through all the Kingdome. All which ſhould moue all of vs of this Land (if we haue not loſt all life of motion) euen now to turne vnto the Lord with all our hearts. And therefore, for my par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, and to ſet my ſelfe (ſome ſteps) forward inſo good a way, I haue left this little pawne in the Sanctuary for mine own engagement. Where, I deſire you (Good <hi>Miſtreſle DANET</hi>) to goe on in the ſame good way, you haue been long vpon, and that till you finiſh your courſe: which, that it may be with true comfort, to your Bliſſe eternall, I will pray (as I daily doe) while we haue being together. The time cannot be long to you or me: which ſhould make vs therfore (and I pray God we may be made;) to redeeme all the good houres of it for the power of godlineſſe and a pure conuerſation in Chriſt. Which gift alſo I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly craue at Gods hands for thoſe you haue Adopted into your family, as the charge of your prouidence: that, to Gods pleaſure, they may longer yet haue the comfort of you, your Tenants in like manner, and that whole Neighbour-hood, in that light which now you beare vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them by your life in the Goſpel, and your beeing in the world, He ſaith <hi>Amen</hi> vnto it,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Clon-bury neere Ludlow; <date>
                     <hi>Iune</hi> 1. 1625.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Who is yours truly for his beſt meanes in the Word of Faith.
ROBERT HORN.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:17070:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>AN ADMONITION TO ALL <hi>ENGLAND:</hi> More ſpecially to LONDON <hi>and other Cities and townes in</hi> England, where the death of Plague hath (lately) beene. (<g ref="char:dtristar">*⁎*</g>)</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>IOHN 5.14.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>After theſe things Ieſus findeth him in the Temple, and ſaid vnto him; behold thou art made whole: Sinne no more leſt a worſe thing come vnto thee.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Scripture is a Scripture of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition, and containeth matter of important counſell; which, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to a man whom Chriſt loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from his chaine of a long ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, concerneth vs to amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that are ſicke of ſinne. <hi>Hee was held in his infirmity thirty and eight yeeres: verſe</hi> 5. ſome of vs haue beene held longer in the chaine of our
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:17070:4"/>ſinnes. Now, after he was cured, (not knowing by whom) he was found in the Temple, to wit by Chriſt who cured him. And ſo, hauing ſtrangely, and by mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle, without meanes, receiued health and power to walke, he walkes to the Temple, (the houſe of prayer and praiſe) probably, (I thinke I may ſay purpoſely) to giue thankes for his corporall health, and to pray for ſpirituall. Doing ſo; his Phyſition, who had done one good worke vpon him, purpoſing to doe another, and better in the cure of his ſoule, returnes (after he had, for a while, withdrawne himſelfe) and comes to the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, where he found his Patient. Being found there, he beginnes (inſtantly) the cure of ſinne in his ſoule: puts him in remembrance how long a ſeruant he had beene to ſinne vnder an old infirmity; and telling him what a bleſſing he had receiued in his body, which was made whole, wiſheth him to haue care of his ſoule by brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king off his ſinnes, or the courſe he held in them, after the courſe of the world: which, if he did not, would coſt him deare, for a worſe thing then matter of ſickneſſe would befall him in a worſe place: at leaſt, whom God could not amend with his Rod of correction, he would breake with his yron rod, puniſhing him yet <hi>ſeuen times more,</hi> that is, <hi>grieuouſly, for his ſinnes, Leuit.</hi> 26.18. Thus I haue opened the Text, which is the effect of the miracle here wrought; &amp; ſheweth where Chriſt found the Man, whom he had made whole; and what he ſaid vnto him: for the firſt; it hath two circumſtances; as of time, when he was found, and of perſon, who found him: for the ſecond; it containeth a precept, <hi>ſinne no more;</hi> and the reaſons perſwading it: and they are; the benefit he had receiued, <hi>thou art made whole;</hi> and the perill, if he ſinned ſtill; <hi>a worſe thing would come vnto him.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:17070:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The circumſtance of time, in this word <hi>Afterward,</hi> or <hi>after theſe things,</hi> being a word of context, and refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to the ninth verſe before, ſheweth what it was, that more ſpecially, moued this Man, at this time, to viſit Gods Temple, and to be found in it; and that is the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of him by Chriſt vpon a word ſpeaking: <hi>riſe, take vp thy bed and walke, v.</hi> 8. But I wil take vp no longer time, either for the further opening of this ſentence, which is not hard; or for the taking in of Texts in coherence with this, which is not neceſſarie. And therefore I paſſe to the Doctrines of this verſe, their grounds or reaſons, with their Vſe, and Application.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Afterward.</head>
               <p>THat is, after this cure wrought, and perſon healed, Chriſt findes him in the houſe of prayer, and (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning) found him thankefull: which Precedent deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth followers;
<note place="margin">Doct.</note> and teacheth vs after a benefit receiued from God, to be thankfull to him: greatly after a great benefit; and preſently, after any. So <hi>Melchizedech</hi> bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed God for <hi>Lot</hi> recouered by <hi>Abraham, Gen.</hi> 14.20. and <hi>Moſes</hi> and the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> ſang vnto him in praiſe for the <hi>Egyptian</hi> yoke broken, <hi>Exod.</hi> 15.1, 2, 3, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and the <hi>Iewes</hi> kept a feaſt of memoriall for their ſafety and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of their enemies, and of that wicked <hi>Haman, Heſt.</hi> 9.17. In <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.15. <hi>Dauid</hi> deſireth God to giue him cauſe and matter, and then promiſeth to praiſe God with ioyfull lippes; not diuiding betweene the effect and cauſe. Hence further, he debates with himſelfe about rendring to God in this manner, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.12. and, in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother <hi>Pſalme,</hi> ſummons all within him to this duty, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.1. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ioynes with prayer thankeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing by an inſeparable tie, <hi>Philip.</hi> 4.6. and good reaſon:
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:17070:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>for, as he ſaith; <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 4.6. praiſe ſets the watch in our prayers, without which they would fall aſleepe in our mouthes: the Scripture is full in this point: the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons:</p>
               <p>Wee ſit at an eaſie rent by ſuch a returne:<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſons </seg>1</label> for, what eaſier then to confeſſe the liberality of ſuch a <hi>Land-lord</hi> by taking words vnto vs, and by ordering our waies? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.23. Secondly,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> thankfulneſſe ſanctifieth all our receipts, without which they are vncleane vnto vs, <hi>Exodus</hi> 12.14. and no better then ſtollen waters, <hi>Pro.</hi> 9.17. Thirdly,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> true Chriſtians muſt ſtand in ſome di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance from Hypocrites, and diſſemblers with God: the difference ſtands in point of praiſe, and not of petition: for, Hypocrites can make a good ſhew in prayer: their neceſſities and deſire of ſupply will kindle a fire of ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtneſſe this way, <hi>Luke</hi> 17.13. but, when they ſhould returne with acknowledgement, <hi>where are they? verſe</hi> 17. Fourthly,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> prayer is a ſweet oblatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to God: but the ſoule of it, and that which quickens it, is true thankfulneſſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.23. and heere, what the body is without the ſoule; that is, prayer for a benefit, and no praiſe for it. Fifthly,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> of all the Sacrifices in the Law, this of praiſe was moſt acceptable to God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.13.14. which made our fathers in the eſtate of the Old Teſtament, often, and in many words to vow this oblation to God, and (as it were) to enter into bond vnto him to pay it, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 66.13.14. <hi>Eccleſiaſt.</hi> 5.4.5. Sixthly,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> if nothing elſe could moue vs to be thankfull after a benefit, yet our owne good by the hand, ſhould; for, the remembrance of an old benefit prepares the way for a new: and what elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence more forcible to draw from a man what wee craue or need, then the ſhewing of our ſelues thankfull for what we haue had already? God ſets no other rent-charge
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:17070:5"/>vpon all he giues (who giues all freely) but the old rent of a thankfull heart, and of thankfulneſſe in our liues: and, if this be done, we ſhall be ſure to be great gainers at Gods hands. Seuenthly,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> we are thankfull to men for ſmall matters: and ſhall we be vnthankful to him that giues vs all things? ſhall the wicked Heathen praiſe their gods of ſiluer, and gold, of braſſe, of yron, of wood, &amp; ſtone, who were made themſelues, <hi>Dan.</hi> 5.4. and ſhall not we praiſe that God that made vs, and all the world?</p>
               <p>The Vſe of this is for all <hi>England:</hi>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> but more ſpecially for <hi>London,</hi> and other Townes and Cities vpon which the Sword of Peſtilence hath bin lately laid: for, ſhould not theſe be found in the Temple with this man, healed by Chriſt? And, for <hi>London,</hi> the prime Citie of the Kingdome; ſeeing that ſo lately, the waies of it ſo la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, being al ſhut vp, <hi>Lam.</hi> 1.4. which now clap hands for their opening againe, and for their being ſowen with the ſeed of man: ſhould it not regiſter in marble of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance a worke of mercy toward it, ſo ſingular, and ſo ſtrange? ſhould it not cry grace, grace vnto it? <hi>Zach.</hi> 4.7. for, from 44.63. dead and buried of the mortality of Plague in one weeke, in that Citie, the Bill fell in few weekes to no leſſe then halfe a ſcore; yea to foure onely: and can ſuch an abatement, ſo wondered at, proue as the wonder that laſts but nine daies? Rather, may not the Citizens, and may we not all ſay (this admirable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe conſidered) as the people of <hi>Sion</hi> in captiuity, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their returne, ſaid: <hi>We were like them that dreame? Pſal.</hi> 126.1. Surely, we cannot denie, that our mouth is filled with laughter, and our tongues with ſongs, <hi>v.</hi> 2. and, ſhall they be empty of his praiſe, who hath done ſo great things for vs, whereof we ſing? <hi>v.</hi> 3. When <hi>Ioſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ah</hi> had made a great ſlaughter of <hi>Amaleck</hi> and his men;
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:17070:6"/>euen ſo great and ſo long as <hi>Moſes</hi> his feeble hands could be held from falling downe, which was <hi>till the Sunne went downe, Exod.</hi> 17.12. Gods charge to <hi>Moſes</hi> was, that it ſhould be written, for better remembrance, in a booke, and rehearſed to <hi>Ioſhuah, verſe</hi> 14. This was a great bleſſing of God, and this ſo great bleſſing of his, muſt, both be written and ſpoken of: was it a bleſſing bookeable, which God ſhewed to <hi>Iſrael</hi> againſt <hi>Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leck,</hi> who waſted ſo many of his weake and feeble peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple? and, is it not worthy (both) to bee ſpoken of and bookt with letters of laſting praiſe in our hearts and mouthes, that God hath, in manner, remoued, ſo cleane and quickly, from a Citie of ſo great vſe to the whole Realme, that <hi>Amaleck</hi> of waſting Peſtilence? But our dulneſſe hath need of much ſpurring, and and of thoſe nailes that <hi>Salomon</hi> (the wiſeſt King and wiſeſt Man) ſpake of, faſtned by the <hi>Maſters of the Aſſemblies, Eccleſ.</hi> 12.13. for, how ſoone had we forgotten a worke of this nature, (a worke all made of mercy) by quitting <hi>London,</hi> as now, of the mortality of 3300. and odde, falling there of a like ſtroake of Plague in one weeke, and in the yeere 1603. This, for ſome yeeres after, lay dead, and as buried in ſome perpetuall graue: therefore hath God opened our graues againe, by killing with the Plague of Peſtilence in that ſame Citie, and thereabouts, from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>Aprill</hi> or after, to the 15. of <hi>December,</hi> 1625. no fewer then 35417. And I pray God this may be a war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning for thoſe of <hi>London,</hi> and of all <hi>England</hi> to keepe better in remembrance, and to better purpoſe the Acts of Gods mercy; and to keepe both them and vs from falling after the like manner of diſobedience. If it be not; and if ſtill we will proue vnfaithfull; though the Plague were quite gone; God hath other Vultures (as one ſaith)
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:17070:6"/>to ſend vpon the carion of a Realme, dead in ſinnes, and treſpaſſes: for, beſide the Plague of Peſtilence, he hath his glittering Sword (which is a grieuous Plague) that he can put into the hand of an enemy of a fierce counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and of an implacable deſire to our Land. But God turne away the euill: and to doe our parts to doe it; let the laſt grieuouſly deuouring Peſtilence in and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>London,</hi> and in other Cities and Townes abroad be, the <hi>graue of our luſts, Num.</hi> 11.34. and let a ſound confeſſion of ſinnes, and turning to God from ſinne, burie them: elſe, it will be but to a greater hardning, that the Lord in his ſingular mercy, at his laſt great aſſiſe of commune mortality, reprieued vs, pulling ſome then, <hi>as a brand out of the fire, Zacharie</hi> 3.2.</p>
               <p>A reproofe of thoſe who bury Gods benefits ſo deep in Sepulchers of obliuion, that,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vſe</hi> 2.</note> (like as it fared with the <hi>nine clenſed Lepers, Luke</hi> 17.17.) there is no returning to giue thankes. Many in ſome plunges of ſickneſſe (as diſſembling Saylors in a ſtorme) will fall to their deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; who yet, (when the weather is ouer, and a calme skie of health ſucceedes) drowne all remembrance of the danger, then, in their prophane Cannes of Wine and Beere. Then, (as vnthankfull Sea-men) inſteede of fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding them in the Temple, you may finde them in ſome Ale-houſe or Tauerne, toſſing their Cannes to the health of the diuell. What is this but to receiue a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing from God, and to thanke the diuell for it? but, what man beſtowing a benefit vpon vs, and looſing his thankes, will ſend another after it? and, can we imagin God will, when men deale with him like thoſe vnthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> whoſe prayers and praiſe ended almoſt aſſoone as they had paſſed the red ſea? The Heathen did offer continually vnto their falſe Gods their cynamon
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:17070:7"/>and frankinſence: and ſhall it be enough for vs, or will it diſcharge vs, for a day, or ſome few daies, and that in no true meaning, to offer our tribute of praiſe to IE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>HOVAH, the true God, who is worthy, (and onely) to be ſerued in righteouſneſſe and true holineſſe all the daies of our life? <hi>Luke</hi> 1.75. Shall wee thus requite the Lord, <hi>as a people fooliſh and vnwiſe? Deut.</hi> 52.6. vnthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe is a cloſe Thiefe: and will wee ſo cunningly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue God (indeed our ſelues) by robbing him of the praiſe that is due vnto his name? Rather, ſhould we not extoll him with our lippes, and with our liues praiſe him? But who will not ſay, that he thankes God for all? To whom I ſay: true thankfulneſſe ſtands not in words, but in obedience to Gods Word: nor in ſaying, but in giuing thankes: nor in labour of lippes, but in purity of life. Then, to come to an iſſue. Thou ſayeſt thou than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt God for all: but art thou a repentant and amen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſinner? when God openeth his treaſury, doſt thou open thy mouth, and art thou liberall of his praiſes, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 66.16.17. rather, and contrarily; when hee ſhoureth bleſſings vpon thee, doſt thou not drop thankes vnto him; praiſing him ſlenderly, when he giues to thee plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſly? or, is not thy thankes cold thanks, and thanks onely in words; not zealous from the heart, nor faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full with a ſingle heart? further, doſt thou thanke God with continuance; not churliſhly, and with the thankes that hath ſoone done? doeſt thou praiſe God with thy praiſe-worthy life? Is thy tongue an inſtrument of the truth, and of his honour? Is his word thy counſellor? are his beſt Seruants thy beſt Companions? his Sabbath daies, thy beſt daies? his Communion Cup thy ſwee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Cup? his Seruice thy liberty? and his yoke thy crowne, and thy glory? If this bee ſo; thou maiſt bee
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:17070:7"/>numbered among the thankfull to God: but if not ſo, &amp; thou be ſtill the ſame man thou waſt: a drunkard ſtill, a fornicator ſtill, ſtill a ſwearer, and prophaner of Gods Name and Sabbaths; a cold hearer or no hearer of the Word, and at Prayer and Sacraments carnall: ſo often as thou ſayeſt; The Lord bee thanked, thy mouth doth not bleſſe God, but mock him: for, out of the ſame mouth proceedeth bleſſing and curſing, praiſe and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfulneſſe, <hi>Iames</hi> 3.10. So much for the circumſtance of the time, that of the Perſon followeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Ieſus.</head>
               <p>IF you aske who found this Man? it was <hi>Ieſus:</hi> if you aske where? it was <hi>in the Temple;</hi> the place where the meanes of Gods publike worſhip were. In ſpeaking of the perſon, I will ſpeake of both together: the perſon is <hi>Ieſus,</hi> in engliſh, the <hi>Sauiour:</hi> the Temple was the houſe of publique prayer and ſacrifices; firſt built by <hi>Salomon:</hi> but after deſtroyed by the King of <hi>Babel,</hi> and re-built by <hi>Zerubbabel</hi> and <hi>Nehemiah.</hi> Heere Chriſt reuealed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,
<note place="margin">Doct.</note> who (before) was not knowne of the Man whom he had healed: which teacheth, that in Church-aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies Chriſt is found, and finds vs. In this way, and to ſuch as are in it he reueales himſelfe in the arme of his Word, <hi>Eſay</hi> 53.1. and as they whom he healed corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, were in the way by which he paſſed, <hi>Mat.</hi> 20.30.34. <hi>Mar.</hi> 6.55.56. ſo they muſt be found in the walke of <hi>Ieſus,</hi> the way of the meanes, whom he will heale ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually. His ordinary walke is in the Temple of the New Teſtament; that is, in the publique aſſembly of Chriſtians. Thither (therefore) we muſt come, if wee will know Chriſt in the arme of power to our Saluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>Dauid</hi> knew the way by his experience, and follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed it with loue to the Temple. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 42.1.4. and, when
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:17070:8"/>
                  <hi>Saul</hi> (his Father in law) tooke this way from him by ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment for ſome time; how doth he deſire his returne thither by more then an ordinary affection? for, hee fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as a woman, ſet a longing after ſomewhat, which (becauſe ſhe cannot obtaine) maketh her ſick of deſire, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84.2. There Gods euidences were kept, and there God was in place by an extraordinary preſence: hence, the Prophet was taken vp with a loue thereof, euen to the fainting of his ſoule: he had drunke deepe of Gods bleſſings in that earthly heauen; which being denied him by a kinde of excommunication out of that Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe of God, firſt vnder <hi>Saul,</hi> and then vnder <hi>Abſolom</hi> his owne ſonne; how ſoule-ſick was he for the daily ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices? <hi>Moſes,</hi> when the people of God were kept with <hi>Pharaos</hi> ſtrong hand, as with a chaine in Egypt, from ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing at ſome publique Altar, asketh their deliuerance of the King, leſt the Lord ſhould meete them with Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilence or ſword, <hi>Exod.</hi> 5.3. and ſo, vpon paine of death, God muſt be publikely ſerued; which, if our bodies eſcape, our ſoules ſhall not. Thus it was in the Law and vnder <hi>Moſes.</hi> In the New Teſtament, in like manner, it was the practiſe of Chriſtians to beate this way to the Lord, <hi>Luke</hi> 4.16. and why did they ſo aſſemble, and ſo many in houſes, which they called Synagogues, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were, vpon promiſe, perſwaded there to meet the Lord Chriſt, who would be in the middes of them? <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.20. At another time, the whole Citie came to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in a like aſſembly, and to a like end, <hi>Act.</hi> 13.43.44. and for this, the aſſembly is called Gods Army, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110.3. becauſe God takes the muſter of his people there. But further, for this meeting wee haue a commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and day ſet, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.17.18. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.1. Thus (then) we haue traced the way in which we may finde and bee
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:17070:8"/>found of Chriſt: euen the Kings high-way which fooles cannot miſſe, and which none, but worſe then fooles, goe out of, <hi>Eſay</hi> 35.8. the reaſons:<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſons </seg>
                  </label>
               </p>
               <p>There is <hi>Iacobs</hi> Ladder in the ſtaires of the means to heauen,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 28.12.17. there God hath commanded the bleſſing, and life for euer, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 133.3. Secondly,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> it is our Fathers houſe, <hi>Iohn</hi> 2.16. and where doe children conuerſe familiarly with their earthly Fathers, but at home in their Fathers houſe? where haue they the helps of naturall life, but there? and in what houſe, but therein? And ſhall wee not care to goe home to GOD, our heauenly Father, in the Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie; where we may haue him to ſpeake kindely to vs by his Word; where wee may ſpeake familiarly to him in our prayers; where wee may meete with his ſeales of aſſurance, and be bettered by his nurture &amp; rod of diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline; where he giues vs his Sonne, and giues vs his Spirit, and grace in our hearts? where hee keepes his wealth, and where his houſhold-ſtuffe lies? or doe wee not care for the abundance of Gods houſe? or had we rather liue beggerly in the world, then richly at Church? to be ſhort; had wee rather looſe our gracious Father then finde him, or be found of him in the way, wherein <hi>they that ſeeke finde, Mat.</hi> 7.7. we ſhould be followers of God: and wil we be followers of thoſe, who chooſe ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Father in their ordinary abſences from the Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, then they haue, who aſſemble willingly in the day of Gods muſters? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110.3. Thirdly, hence,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> when <hi>Cain</hi> was caſt out of <hi>Adams</hi> houſe, which was the Church then, he ſaid to God; <hi>I am caſt out of thy ſight, Gen.</hi> 4.14. mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his face in the Aſſembly, which is the Church now.</p>
               <p>But is Chriſt found in Church-Aſſemblies?<note place="margin">Vſe.</note> and doth he there ſeeke vs? and ſeeke vs for much good to our
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:17070:9"/>ſelues? how vnwiſe are we, and what fooles for our ſelues, if we will ſuffer euery twiſt of occaſion, though in neuer ſo ſmall a thred, to hold vs from thence? If a mortall King ſhould ſeeke vs in ſome ſpeciall place to beſtow honours, and wealth vpon vs; and we (knowing the place) would not come thither, were we not both vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dutifull to him, and vnwiſe to our ſelues? This is the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry caſe of our Papiſts Recuſant, and Proteſtants at large. The immortal King of kings ſeekes them in our Church-Aſſemblies to make them rich in Chriſt, and great in Heauen: yet they will not be in place, nor tread vpon the threſhold of his Sanctuarie, ſaue where Law binds; nor ſome, nay many, where they are ſo bound. Of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uids</hi> affection to the publike places of prayer, hearing the Word, receiuing the Sacraments, and the like, wee heard. The riuer of his deſires riſing mainely in this caſe, could be kept within no banke: he could reſt vpon no ground, till, being in exile from Gods Tabernacle, he was brought backe againe to God in his ordinances. It was his Croſſe, and a weighty one vpon him, that by tyrannie, and enforced abſence, hee was not permitted to worſhip at <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi> But now, who doth not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count it the leaſt of his trouble, that by ſickneſſe, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther impediments neceſſitated, not procured, he is held, as in bonds, from the publique Aſſembly? who wiſheth for his appearance before the Lord, <hi>as the Hart brayeth for the brooks of water? Pſal.</hi> 42.1. who now feareth the hand of the Lord (that of which we heard) for omitting the publique Seruice of God in the Congregation? and not holden from it by <hi>Pharao,</hi> as ſome neceſſary chaine in Egypt, but with chaines of their owne, either vnne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary buſines, or carnall ſports? <hi>Exod.</hi> 5.2. It was <hi>Dauids</hi> deſire, aboue, or more then all he deſired, to dwell in the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:17070:9"/>houſe of the Lord all his time, <hi>and to behold the beauty of the Lord in his Temple, Pſal.</hi> 27.4. wee make no ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, nor will we take vp our pleaſant daies with ſuch ſad matters. And ſome, though they dwell not far from the place, where the Arke of the Goſpel is placed in the Preaching Miniſters mouth, as in the Tabernacle there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; yet, if the wether be not to their lazie minds, if any impediment ſeaze them; a leſſe matter then the buying of a Farme, or the prouing of fiue yoke of Oxen, wil keep them away, <hi>Luke</hi> 24.18.19. you muſt haue them excuſed; they cannot: but more truly, they wil not come: &amp; why? they can ſerue God at home, as well as there: ſo could <hi>Abraham</hi> as eaſily, as haue gone the dolorous iourney of three daies, to Sacrifice his deareſt Son <hi>Iſaac, Gen.</hi> 22.4. but <hi>Abraham</hi> muſt go, and <hi>Abraham</hi> did go to the place which God ſhewed him. And ſo God will be ſerued in the place he hath ſhewed vs, and in the manner, &amp; as we haue heard of him: there we muſt offer vp, not the only childe of our loues, <hi>but the foule children of our luſts, Iames</hi> 1.15. &amp; that vpon the Altar of the law that threatneth ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities and ſins. The <hi>Iewes</hi> came betimes to <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> though dwelling in the vttermoſt liſts of the Land: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther foule weather, nor perill by that long way could hinder them: for, with <hi>Abraham,</hi> they droue away al vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane fowles of exception, that might fall vpon the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kaſſes that were for that ſacrifice them, <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.11. But now, <hi>Dauids</hi> place is empty: O Lord, how long? which, though <hi>Sauls</hi> now do not marke, as <hi>Saul</hi> then; God doth: &amp; the Pews &amp; Seats that are empty ſo often, and for no cauſe he knowes, who will one day ſay: wherefore come not theſe to meate, neither yeſterday nor to day? 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 20.27. I may adde, and ſay; not theſe ſeuen or eight weekes of daies? And here let me ſpeake to ſuch vnwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:17070:10"/>and preſt men (where, God will haue none in his camp but voluntaries, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110.3.) what would ſuch do, if the<note n="*" place="margin">Maſter Widley his Tract on the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>abbath. page <hi>125.</hi>
                  </note>
Pariſian line were ſtretched ouer the land, &amp; men ſhould be killed with their bibles in their hands, their blood being ſprinkled vpon the ſeats they ſit on? would they not ſay: this euill is (all) of the Lord, &amp; why ſhould we waite on the Lord any longer, 2. <hi>King.</hi> 6.33. But to make ſhort: yee that thus turne the back and not your faces to Gods Sanctuary, &amp; ſacred houſe; conſider your waies, and turne your feete vnto Gods teſtimonies: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider who it is that ſeekes you, and where, and for what. He that ſeekes you is <hi>Ieſus,</hi> he that ſaues his people, and muſt you, if you will not be damned: and he ſeekes you in the aſſembly: and there ſeeks you for your own good. I ſay therfore, would you be found of God in peace; or of your Sauiour (the Sonne of God) to your peace and comfort euerlaſting: be in the way of the meanes: let your feete ſtand within the gates of the Goſpels <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem:</hi> there fall downe low on your faces, <hi>and kneele be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: he Lord your Maker, Pſal.</hi> 95.6. And God perſwade <hi>Iapheth</hi> to dwell in the tents of <hi>Shem, Gen.</hi> 9.27. But there are many out-lyers, and many, who when they ſhould dwell in <hi>Shems</hi> Tent, at the times of publike prayer and hearing, dwell in the tents of <hi>Cham,</hi> where their other impieties are accompliſhed and made vp with their ſcof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fings at <hi>Noah,</hi> the Preacher of righteouſneſſe O, how hardly are ſuch perſwaded to be in the Temple with <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meon</hi> and <hi>Anna, Luk.</hi> 2.27.38. or to be found in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to bee healed, as this man whom Chriſt healed? but <hi>Ieſus</hi> ſeekes them there, and they looſe him in the world, and in wordly luſts of profit and pleaſures. God and Prince require their preſence: God vpon paine of death; &amp; the Prince vpon pain of twelue pence for euery
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:17070:10"/>day: yet neither God nor Prince can be heard; and how ſhall I?</p>
               <p>So much for the place where this man was found, with the circumſtances of time and perſon; it followeth to conſider, what Chriſt ſaid.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <q>And ſaid vnto him, behold, &amp;c.</q>
               <p>IN theſe words that Chriſt ſpake vnto the Man, wee haue a precept, and reaſons perſwading it: the precept in theſe words; <hi>Sinne no more:</hi> the reaſons are two, as firſt the benefit of his health, <hi>thou art made whole;</hi> and the threatning of a worſe matter, if he ſhould ſin afterwards as before: <hi>leſt a worſe thing come vnto thee:</hi> for the firſt of the reaſons; we haue the benefit it ſelfe, and finger at it, in the word; <hi>behold.</hi> After our Sauiour had cured this man, he preſently left him, as appeareth in the next verſe before; now he returnes againe, as not meaning to bee long hid, that his power might be knowne, &amp; his ſtrange worke had in remembrance: which therefore made him to ſay; <hi>behold,</hi> as leading him by the hand to a deeper co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of what was done vpon him: as if he had ſaid; thou was't tyed to thy bed with a long infirmity of eight and thirty yeeres continuance: now this tie is looſed by him that ſaid vnto thee; <hi>riſe, take vp thy bed and walke, v.</hi> 8. and now thou art noe longer bound to thy bed, but free to God: remember and forget not: or <hi>behold;</hi> that is, intend thy thoughts to this worke of thy cure, paſſing ſome pauſe vpon it. This I take to be the meaning of our Sauiour in theſe words: <hi>behold thou art made whole:</hi> which teacheth that chriſtians ſhould not paſſe ouer Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings towards them in his noble Acts, either of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy or iuſtice with a careleſſe, or blinde eye. In <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32. the word <hi>Selah,</hi> which is a word of attention, repeated three times, as <hi>ver.</hi> 4.5.7. importeth as much: and, what God
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:17070:11"/>did againſt <hi>Amaleck</hi> (Gods peoples enemie) muſt as we heard, be written in a booke or regiſter, <hi>Ex.</hi> 17.14. and in <hi>Deut.</hi> 25.17. it muſt be written, what God did that way, in ſure tables of laſting memory. So <hi>Samuel,</hi> taking a ſtone, and pitching it betweene <hi>Mizphe</hi> and <hi>Shen,</hi> called it by the name of
<note n="*" place="margin">Eben-Ezer.</note> hitherto the Lord hath holpen vs, 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.12. The like ſtone of help for memorie, did the Iewes ſet vp in an extraordinary holy day to God for his deliuering of them from the butchery of <hi>Haman, Heſt.</hi> 9.17.18. And <hi>Dauid</hi> brought his heart to an edge by ſuch diligent booking of Gods daily mercies: for, fighting the Lords battells, he ſet down, as in a commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie or iuſt volume, the Geſts and Acts of euery daies march to the praiſe of God. The book of Pſalmes ſhew's he had the pen of a ready writer, this way: the reaſons:</p>
               <p>One maine end of God,<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſons </seg>
                  </label> in his ſtrange workes of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and iuſtice,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> is to open our eyes and to prouoke conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration: and ſhall God come ſo neere, in them, to eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of vs, and we take no view of him in obiects of ſo great light?<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.22. Secondly, he that made all, doth all for himſelfe; <hi>Pro.</hi> 16.4. that is, that his workes might praiſe him, who is onely worthy to be praiſed, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145.10. but how ſhall we giue him the reſpects of his power, praiſe, goodnes, and infinite glory, when in his workes that are wonderfull, we obſerue little or nothing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after; and when, from things that are ſtranger then we thought of, and greater then we lookt for, wee draw no matter to admire his wiſedome ſo, as we be guided by it; or to magnifie his power ſo, as we repoſe vpon it? and heere, tell me if it be not a diſgrace to an expert worke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, hauing made ſome excellent peece, that his friend ſhould paſſe by, with contempt, with neglect at leaſt, not vouchſafing to looke vpon it? To apply therfore: is
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:17070:11"/>this a diſgrace, being offered to man who works imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly? what is it then, not to haue in eſteeme the workes of God, ſo perfectly wrought? And (here) <hi>Salomons</hi> coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel is, (and it is good counſel;) conſider the work of God, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.13. Thirdly,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> when men comming into ſome ſhop, behold ſome curious work; they paſſe by it (know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it made not it ſelf;) and enquire after him that made it: and ſhall we looking into the ſhop of Gods workes, that are all excellent, looſe our ſight in them, neuer loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king away to the moſt excellent work-man, IEHOVAH our Creator? Fourthly, if God doe nothing in vaine; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> then what he doth alwaies to purpoſe, muſt be thought of accordingly, by the aſſiſtance and helpe of our beſt meditation, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 111.4.</p>
               <p>An inſtruction therfore to gather matter from all Gods works,<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> (eſpecially ſuch as are ſtrangely wrought) to our help in this duty: when we ſee iudgements executed in the land, we muſt put them down in our memories, as in ſome book, that we may feare and be humbled by them: or, if God work mercifully in our kingdome, as he lately did by quenching ſo ſtrangely thoſe coales of Plague he caſt into <hi>London,</hi> and by opening that Fountaine of tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that was ſo choakt vp in the laſt Viſitation by Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilence: we muſt not forget his louing kindneſſe to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue it for his praiſe, <hi>whoſe mercy endureth for euer.</hi> The Prophet, the Author of the 147. and 148. <hi>Pſalmes,</hi> was trained vp in this Schoole, &amp; learned very much by the wiſdome and iuſtice that he found in all Gods workes. And ſurely, if we would go to Schoole, but to our daily experience in this kinde, hauing eyes ſuch as this Man of God had, and vſing our diligence ſo as he did, we ſhould not be ſo fooliſh &amp; ignorant, and as beaſts before God.</p>
               <p>The very heathen, that were without the word, and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:17070:12"/>had no other bookes but the workes of God to reade in, did in them ſee ſomewhat of the true God, though not to his glory by the wiſedome which is of him, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.20. And ſhall we learne nothing of God, who haue not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the darke booke of his workes to looke vpon, but the booke of a plainer letter, the booke of his word to medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate of? ſhal we become more fooliſh then the wiſer ſort of the heathen were, that onely groped after God in their fooliſh hearts that were full of darkeneſſe, <hi>verſe</hi> 21. And (now) to our purpoſe: doe we thinke, or can wee imagine that God ſent and took away ſo great a fire of Plague, ſaue for ſome few ſparkes that yet remaine here and there vntroden out, only to hold talke of it, and not to feare that God that hath power ouer all Plagues? Then are we as blockiſh as thoſe Iewes, whom <hi>Ieremy</hi> reprooueth for learning nothing of the feare of God by his bleſſings, yea though he reſerued vnto them the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed weekes of the harueſt, <hi>Ier.</hi> 5.24. But Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and all whom the Lord hath made wiſe to their Saluation, wil heare the Rod, and him who hath appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted or betrothed it; <hi>Mich.</hi> 6.9. If the father brings a rod, the fearefull childe will tremble: the whip of Peſtilence is a ſore Rod, &amp; they tremble at it, whom God hath ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. By it, or in ſight of it, they gather themſelues, and all their wits together, taking them vp from their ſtray waies, before the decree (which is at the ſeale) come forth, or be executed againſt them, <hi>Zeph.</hi> 2.1. or they fan &amp; winnow themſelues from the chaffe of ſin, which ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not abide in the winde of the Lords iuſtice, &amp; is driuen to hell with ſinners, and all that forget God. They trie their waies, and bring them to the touch, turning vnto God, <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.40. and ſo are better by the rod, Gods louing correction makes them whole: The wicked not ſo.</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:17070:12"/>
               <p>A reproofe of thoſe who ſet all Gods iudgements, or <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> workes done in iudgement, at naught. There are that deſpiſe counſell, and will none of Gods correction, <hi>Pro.</hi> 1.25. ſuch are neuer the better by his word calling them, nor by the whip laſhing them: whether God be angry or well pleaſed, they are all one. Let the earth be moued, they are not moued, and let the hills tremble, they feare not. In the ſad daies of a Land, cauſed by Peſtilence, dearth, or the rumours of warre, they drinke wine in bowles, and anoint themſelues with the chiefe oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, not troubled for the affliction of <hi>Ioſeph, Am.</hi> 6.6. no aduerſity can make them change their merry note which they chaunt to their inſtruments of muſick, <hi>ver.</hi> 5. and they put the day of euill farre off, <hi>verſe</hi> 3. They con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider not the rod, and prouoke the ſtriker, neither can pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments awe them, nor bleſſings winne them: for puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, if they touch not them, no matter wher they light: and for bleſſings, they take them as gifts of fortune, or with Papiſts, as their due and merit from God: they riſe not by them to obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, &amp; they liue in them to the giuers diſhonor. Hence, ſo few to this day, ſee to any amendment, notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding the ſinger of God, or rather whole hand in ſo grieuousa Plague, or ſtroke vpon <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> neuer the like, or ſo great in any memory now liuing. But though God hath now ſtopped the ſore, that ſo ran &amp; ceaſed not; yet how ſoone he may open it againe, who knowes? &amp; who ſhould not conſider? he is the ſame God that he was euer, and the God that hateth iniquity as much as euer he did. The Peſtilence that was ſo lately ſent, what was it but the fruit of an euill tree, that is, of the Realms ſin? Our Land was all ouer-runne with ſin: Our Cities and great Townes were as the Pot, and the men in them, as the fleſh, ſpoken of by <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> Chap.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:17070:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>11.3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 24.3.4.5. Our Maſters in <hi>Iſrael</hi> were (many of them) no Teachers: and ſome that taught, threw down by euill example what they builded by doctrine, eating and drinking with ſinners, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.49. the poore ſheepe were ſmitten with ignorance: all good fellowſhip was and did conſiſt in pots of drinke, and pipes of ſmoake. In the whole Land there was a large confederacie and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of ſinfull men. The ſinnes of the Churches ſpoken of. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 2. and 3. Chapters, were the ſins of ſome of bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter note in their cold loue of the truth: and for pride, fulnes of bread, and abundance of idleneſſe (the very ſins of <hi>Sodom</hi>) what were they but <hi>Englands</hi> crying ſins? Thus it was with vs, and this wee were, when the late Plague began: and if we fall againe vpon this euill byas of old cuſtome to like ſins or worſe, not remembring Gods late hand, what can we expect but a new Plague, or the old renewed? God hath other roddes of correction in his Schoole, and yron rods to breake vs, if we will not turne at the correction paſt: or if we will ſinne ſtill, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoking God in the Church, and grieuing him in the Common-wealth, the Lord will watch vpon worſe Plagues to bring them among vs: for, when one afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on cannot preuaile, he can ſend another, and many, till we be made better, or confounded, <hi>Leuit.</hi> 26.18.19.</p>
               <p>So much for the finger directing to the benefit: the benefit it ſelfe followeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <q>Thou art made whole.</q>
               <p>CHriſt heere remembers the man of the benefit hee had ſo lately and ſtrangely receiued in his health, which was giuen him, not mediately in the <hi>Poole of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſda,</hi> but immediately by diuine power. And theſe words are the ground of the <hi>ſubſequent</hi> admonition firſt, as if the <hi>Lord Chriſt</hi> had ſaid: ſin made thee ſick, &amp; God
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:17070:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>hath made thee whole; fall not backe to thy ſins paſt, leſt the relapſe make thee worſe then euer. <hi>Queſt.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Queſt. Anſw. Doct.</note> But who made this man whole? <hi>Anſw.</hi> God by his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and Chriſt as God: whence learne, that as God can make ſicke; ſo it is he onely that can make whole. We reade as much in the Text of <hi>Hannabs</hi> ſong; which Text ſpeaketh of a greater matter: for it ſaith; <hi>the Lord killeth and maketh aliue, bringeth downe to the graue, and raiſeth vp,</hi> 1. <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m.</hi> 2.6. Now, it is eaſier to raiſe from ſickneſſe to health, then to bring from death to life. Therefore, <hi>Hezekiah</hi> (King of <hi>Iudah,</hi>) went the right way for health, <hi>when he turned his face to the wall, and prayed vnto the Lord, Eſay</hi> 38.2. hence <hi>Moſes</hi> in his ſong ſaith, what we haue heard <hi>Hanna</hi> in her ſong to ſay, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.39. And the Prophet <hi>Hoſea,</hi> exhorting the people that went farre from God in their ſinnes, to draw back by repentance, giues this for one reaſon, that the <hi>Lord would heale them, Hoſea</hi> 6.1. as if there were no Phyſitian but he, nor balme of healing but by him: further alſo, ſo much the king of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> (none of the beſt, rather one of the worſt) confeſſed, ſaying; that he muſt haue Gods place, who will take vpon him <hi>to heale a man of his Leproſie,</hi> 2. <hi>King.</hi> 5.7. the reaſons:</p>
               <p>Hence,<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſons </seg>
                  </label> our health is commonly and truly called Gods bleſſing: and here corporall Phyſitians,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> or Phyſitians of the body, are as the ſpirituall of the ſoule: for they are but <hi>Miniſters by whom we beleeue,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.5. and ſo, theſe are but Miniſters of health, and God is the giuer: he that maketh an vnbeleeuer faithfull, is he that maketh a ſicke man whole: and this is God, for <hi>Faith is the gift of God, Epheſ.</hi> 2.8. Secondly, ſin cauſeth ſickneſſe,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> and impaiteth health, <hi>Micah</hi> 6.10.13. but God onely forgiueth ſins: it was alledged by the <hi>Scribes,</hi> and not denied by Chriſt, <hi>Mar.</hi> 2.6.7. and therefore he only can take away ſicknes<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and ſend health.</p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:17070:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>An inſtruction to vſe ſuch Phyſitians for our neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> as by whom we may be perſwaded that God, who maketh whole, will ſend a meſſage of health vnto vs. And theſe muſt be men of good conſcience and ſound Religion; not Popiſh, or of no Religion, if wee can chooſe: elſe it will be ſaid: is it not becauſe there is no God in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that yee goe to enquire of the God of <hi>Ekron</hi> for your health? 2. <hi>King.</hi> 1.3. God giueth the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing: and can we thinke that hee will incloſe it to vs in euill meanes? further, hauing made our beſt choiſe this way, we muſt take certaine religious preparatiues, that their phyſick may haue the better worke vpon vs. And here, we muſt humble our ſoules with repentance, and confeſſion of ſinnes: yea craue pardon for them, and forſake them, purpoſing amendment: alſo, we muſt ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie our ſicke beds, and make them vp by the Word of God and prayer, 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.5. The truth is; when a man is made whole, good medicines are good meanes vnto it, but Gods bleſſing is it that ſtrikes the ſtroke of health, and recouers him. Therefore let thoſe who haue lately felt the ſweet fruit of Gods worke, in their reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings to health from the wound of Plague, bring forth like fruit of thankfulneſſe in their turnings to him that hath healed them: elſe better they had died then; and that the Plague had taken away their life, when it tooke away their health. The want of this is (often) cauſe that diſeaſes, curable in themſelues, are made incurable by our ſinnes: which ſhould make vs, when God begins his correction by ſickneſſe, to begin repentance by turning to him that ſmiteth vs: when we take phyſick for our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couery, we muſt not take it as truſting in it, but repoſe on God for health: nor muſt our end of taking it be to put off death further then God hath bounded our terme
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:17070:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>here: for, phyſick can goe no farther then hee hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, who puts his ſtaffe into it without which it falls to nothing.</p>
               <p>A reproofe of thoſe who with <hi>Aſa</hi> in ſickneſſe,<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> ſeeke to phyſitions, and not to God, 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 16.12. or to them in the firſt place, and to God, when there is no other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie. Some neuer call when God bindeth them, <hi>Iob</hi> 1.36.13. bid them pray, they liſt not, or cannot: and for their ſickneſſe, they fret at it, and with <hi>Cain</hi> ſay; <hi>the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment is greater then they can beare, Gen.</hi> 4.13 as if they ſhould ſay: God doth not well ſo to puniſh them; that is, ſo ſeuerely, or ſo for nothing. And ſo, they anger him with their impatiencie, who muſt giue them their health if they euer recouer; and increaſe the wrath, going fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in but not comming out of ſickneſſe to health. But ſome, inſteede of ſeeking the Lord by prayer, ſeeke to the diuel in ſome witch for eaſe of paine, or end of ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: ſo did <hi>Ahaziah,</hi> who falling through a latteſſe in his vpper chamber in <hi>Samaria,</hi> was ſo bruiſed with the fall, that he lay ſick of it vpon his bed, till he died: here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, when he ſhould haue ſent to God in <hi>Iſrael</hi> he ſent to an Idol in <hi>Ekron, Baal-zebub;</hi> that is, not to God in faith, but to the diuell in ſinne, to know if he ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer of that diſeaſe, 2. <hi>King.</hi> 1.2.6.</p>
               <p>The admonition followeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <q>Sinne no more.</q>
               <p>OVr Sauiour, hauing made this Man whole; here, like a good Phyſitian, tells him what dyet hee ſhould keep, to keepe ſo. The dyet preſcribed is; <hi>Sin no more:</hi> the meaning is, not as thou haſt done: and ſo he bidds him not to keepe a courſe in ſinne, as before, and not to returne to the vomit which he hath caſt: or, he wiſheth him to looke better to the health of his ſoule,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:17070:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>for neglect whereof, he had ſuch ill health in his body; and to take heede that by the ill dyet of ſin he fell not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a relapſe. This may be our Sauiours counſell: where yet he intends not that he can be ſo free from ſin, as that he ſhould neuer fall againe; for that is impoſſible in this mid-vaile: but intimates that his ſickneſſe was the fruit of his ſin:<note place="margin">Doct.</note> from whence we may draw this concluſion; that the diſeaſes of the body (for the moſt part) come from the diſeaſe of the minde, cauſed by ſin: and ſo, God correcteth ſin with the whip of ſickneſſe, not alwaies, yet moſt what, and commonly. I ſay not alwaies: for, there are (ſometimes) other cauſes of ſickneſſe beſide ſin, not knowne to vs, but well knowne to God, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 9.2.3 yet ſin (ordinarily) is cauſe. The firſt fall gaue vs this bruiſe, and euer ſince we ſpat blood through or by meanes of it. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, a peace ſince was made betweene God and vs in the <hi>ſeede of the woman, Gen.</hi> 3.15. but it neuer reached ſo far as to conclude a peace betweene God and ſin: and he that was contented to be reconciled to ſinners is at em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity with ſin; hence, ſin is the proper and kindly cauſe of Plagues vpon a whole Nation, or particular perſon; and ſo of ſickneſſes vpon it, and him. And for generall ſtrokes vpon a Land, that ſin cauſeth them, it is a plaine caſe in the book of <hi>Lamentations:</hi> where <hi>Ieremy</hi> ſhewing what a folly it is for man ſo to vexe himſelf, that is, ſo in vaine by miſ-iudging of his eſtate, helps to winde him out of the by-pathes of ſo foule miſtakes; and directly tells him, that being ſmitten of God, hee ſuffereth iuſtly the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of his ſin: <hi>man ſuffereth for his ſin, Lam.</hi> 3.39. but more ſpecially, in the inſtance of ſickneſſes, that theſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo come deſeruedly for ſin, beſide the words here, the ſpeech of Chriſt to the <hi>ſick of the Palſey,</hi> (in which diſeaſe his ſinne held him) doth make plaine as vpon tables,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:17070:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.26. for, firſt he forgaue him his ſins remouing the cauſe, <hi>verſe</hi> 2. and then he healed his Palſey, changing the effect, <hi>ver.</hi> 6. God was comming to <hi>Iudah</hi> with good things in both hands: but hee turned away: the good came not, which their ſins hindered, and euil things were ſent, which their iniquities were cauſe of, <hi>Ier.</hi> 5.25. <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaz</hi> tells <hi>Iob,</hi> that miſery comes not forth of the duſt, <hi>Iob</hi> 5.6. and bids him to ſeeke another mother for it, euen the proper mother of miſerie, which is ſin, <hi>ver.</hi> 3. The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious to Gods ordinances (who are foule ſinners) are threatned, for like matter, by the Lord himſelfe, <hi>Leuit.</hi> 26.15.16. and the Pſalmiſt ſaith that fooles, (by which he meaneth wicked ones) by reaſon of their tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and becauſe of their iniquities are afflicted, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 105.17. that is, afflicted with ſickneſſe, and viſited with troubles, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.32. the reaſons:<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſons </seg>
                  </label>
               </p>
               <p>In many things we ſin all, <hi>Iames</hi> 3.2. and all in ſome:<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> but the leaſt ſin doth, at the beſt hand, deſerue the gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle correction of ſickneſſe, which, hauing the owne due, deſerueth hell and death, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.23. Secondly,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> the euill of puniſhment followeth the euill of ſin: and God can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not make ſuch a breach in his iuſtice, as to ſpare for ſin, when men doe not ſpare to ſin. God is righteous and not mercifull onely: and therefore <hi>Dauids</hi> ſong to him is of his mercy and iuſtice, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 101.1. Thirdly,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> God ſhould doe wrong, if it were not right to viſit mans tranſgreſſion with the rod, and his iniquity with ſtrokes, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.32. but the God of iudgement cannot doe but what iuſt is: and it is iuſt to giue to euery mother her owne childe; that is, correction where it is deſerued, and more, where more is due: therefore, God afflicting for ſin, it followeth that ſin is the deſeruing cauſe of that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction whatſoeuer.</p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:17070:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>An inſtruction in all we ſuffer,<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> whether by ſickneſſe, or otherwaies, to confeſſe the right father, euen that which hath begotten all that with the ſeede of ſin: wee muſt confeſſe our ſins to bee cauſe of all, and learne to profit by the hand to amendment. I ſay then: hath God lately croſt vs in our trades? it is becauſe we traded with ſin: haue our fields kept their Sabbaths? it is becauſe we haue not kept Gods Sabbaths: haue they beene full of weedes? our hearts haue been fuller of the weeds of ſin: hath God touched vs in our bodies? it is, becauſe wee haue ſo diſhonored him in our bodies: doth the Land mourne? and may we not ſay, <hi>becauſe of Oathes, the Land mourneth? Ier.</hi> 23.10. So, for euery ſorrow we muſt ſay; this is our ſorrow; that is, that which we are worthy of, and comes to the right owner, <hi>Ier.</hi> 10.19. If God lay his finger vpon vs, touching vs, in our eſtate with want, or in our name with diſgrace; nay, if he lay his whole hand vpon vs, ſmiting vs with the calamities of Peſtilence, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min, or Sword, we muſt cleare the Lord in al, &amp; in al ſay; <hi>Righteous art thou O Lord, &amp; iuſt are thy iudgements, Pſal.</hi> 119.137. <hi>Dauid,</hi> when it was told him from the Lord by <hi>Nathan,</hi> that euil ſhould be raiſed againſt him out of his owne houſe, that the Sword ſhould be laid vpon it, that his wiues ſhould be defiled, and the childe die, 2. <hi>Sam</hi> 11.12. pleaded to all this no other defence, but <hi>I haue ſinned againſt the Lord, verſe</hi> 13. And he confeſſeth, that when all thoſe iudgements ſhould come and be execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vpon him, which God, by his Prophet, had threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, yet God was free and he in fault. The like confeſſion made <hi>Daniel</hi> for the people, or rather againſt the people for the Lord, in as fearefull a iudgement as could be exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted vpon a Nation; <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.5, 6, 7, 11, 12, 13, 14. which was, that the Lord was iuſt, and that they had deſerued
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:17070:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſomuch and more: what <hi>Dauid</hi> &amp; <hi>Daniel</hi> did in a Plague and calamitie the greateſt vnder heauen, that muſt wee doe in like manner, and iuſtifie the Lord in all his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: for, no iudgement is executed, which is not exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted for ſin: the law reads the ſentence, and God giues it: if God poure out the dregges of his wrath, it is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we are frozen in our dregges of ſin, <hi>Zeph.</hi> 1.12. the earth is filled with cruelty, before God will fill it with water, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6. and 7. <hi>Chap.</hi> and <hi>Sodom</hi> burneth with luſts, before God will burne it with fire, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.20. <hi>&amp;</hi> 19.5.24 25. So <hi>Iudah</hi> ſerueth ſin, before God will giue vp <hi>Iudah</hi> to ſerue in <hi>Babel.</hi> Shee will not ſerue the Lord: for 70. yeeres, therefore, ſhee muſt ſerue a ſtrange Lord, in a ſtrange Land. And now for our ſelues of this Nation; the Lord hath lately broken in by a terrible Plague: and ſhall we think other, but that the ſins were ſtrong and maſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line that called for it? and if ſo: ſhould it not make vs in all that is come, to confeſſe Gods righteouſnes, and our owne open ſhame, becauſe we haue ſinned againſt him? <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.8. ſhould it not make vs to ſearch and trie our waies, and to turne againe vnto the Lord? or make vs to new-caſt our ſelues, that we may be a people, holy to God? <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.14. If wee doe not, rather, if wee will not, what hope, ſin continuing, (the cauſe of Plagues) but that the effect ſhould follow, great Plagues for ſin? ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther God muſt looſe his iuſtice, or we periſh, if wee will not be reformed: this was more largely ſpoken of in my Commentary on <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9 1. <hi>ver.</hi> 10. the words; <hi>there ſhall no euill, &amp;c.</hi> Doctrine and Vſes there.</p>
               <p>A reproofe of thoſe who being vnder the hand of God in their many ſins,<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> neuer giue God glory by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing vnto him his righteouſneſſe, and their iniquities againſt themſelues, but fret at the rod, and open wide a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:17070:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>him that ſtriketh with it: ſo did that reprobate, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.24. who charged his Lord to be a hard man, and an vnreaſonable taker: one that had a very hard law, a law that reaped where it neuer ſowed: if they doe not what he commandeth, the law is intollerable, and who can helpe it? or, whoſe fault is it but his who ſhould haue giuen them better grace? ſo ſay Reprobates; ſo ſaid <hi>Cain,</hi> and that Gods puniſhment was aboue the fault, <hi>Gen</hi> 4.13. The Hypocrite, when God laies ſmart vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, and paies him in iuſtice, for iniquity and for ſins, fareth like a beaſt that is ſticked &amp; hal'd with ropes, vſing neither meekenes nor entreaty, but with roaring and ſtrugling, and ſtraining himſelfe doubleth his paine. He neuer conſiders his ſin, in which he is bound faſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to iudgement, but complaines of his puniſhment; alſo, he flutters like a bird in a Net, when God hath caught him: but, what is gotten by ſtrugling thus vnder Gods hands? they that are ſo impatient vnder the rod, muſt be bound to a forme: and what doe we get by running a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the rocke and ſtone of offence but a daſhing in fitters, with the Plague-ſore of a tormented conſcience? if (then) we will not bee (as the moſt wicked) when wee are in fault, we muſt humbly (as the moſt penitent) ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit when we haue to do with the Lord; reuerencing his iuſt law, and cleering him. If hee follow vs with iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, he is iuſt: or, if he reiect vs, he is iuſt, holy, and righteous. If he take away our corne in the time of har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt, he may doe it, ſin prouoking him: if hee bring the Plague againe, why may he not, who taking it away in mercy, may in iuſtice, reduce it for ſinne? if he kill with death, we cannot complaine, the wages of ſinne being in our hands, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.23. and the iſſues of it in his.</p>
               <p>The laſt reaſon perſwading, followeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:17070:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <q>Leſt a worſe thing come vnto thee.</q>
               <p>THis laſt reaſon goeth off with a threatning ſhot. It hath a full charge, telling the man whom Chriſt hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, that if he did ſo againe, that is, ſo as before, he ſhould not carry it ſo eaſily: or then, it ſhould bee worſe with him then euer, God hauing an yron rod to breake thoſe, whom his rod of correction cannot make better. And indeed, the Lord hath many iudgments in his ſtore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe that can neuer be emptied. If a man will not bee ſaid vnto by one or two warnings, he can ſend vnto him by his great ordnance. If fickneſſe will not amend a land, if deare markets cannot, there is a worſe thing behind. And ſo we ſee, when one affliction can do nothing,<note place="margin">Doct.</note> God will ſend many and worſe: if a light correction will not moue vs, he hath a heauier rod: and when one cannot, many ſhall. This is a plaine caſe, as appeareth, <hi>Leuit.</hi> 26.18. where <hi>Moſes</hi> threatning, or God by him, obdurate ſinners, tells them, if they will not keepe their hearts ſof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and more ſteepe in obedience to him; hee will pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh them ſeuen times more, that is, more and further, and that according to their ſins. The like is threatned againſt the like perſons by the ſame <hi>Moſes, Deut.</hi> 28.58.59. where, in the perſon of the Lord, the obſtinate and ſinners are told, that they ſhall haue, as their purchaſe and merit, many ſtrokes and wonderfull, yea wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly durable, if they perſiſt to ſinne againſt that great and fearefull name, the Lord their God. In the next verſe the 60. he holds on with more. And in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32.10. the Prophet ſpeakes not of few ſorrowes, as crooks, to pull in the wicked when they offer to breake from God, but of many. I ſay therfore, go as farre as thou wilt, if thou
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:17070:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>go from God, he can fetch thee againe from any of all the quarters of the earth, with many, yea innumerable ſorrowes: the reaſons:<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſons </seg>
                  </label>
               </p>
               <p>Euen our earthly Parents,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> where a little correction twenty: and ſhall our heauenly Father doe leſſe, when gentler meanes can doe nothing?<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, for this, the Lord hath his ſtore-houſe of iudgements, and a whole treaſury of Plagues, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.34. hee hath a hammer to breake the ſtone, <hi>Ier.</hi> 23.29. and a rod of yron to breake the horrible ſinner, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 2.27. Hee will bee a moth to <hi>Ephraim,</hi> and ſo conſume him inſenſibly, by little and little, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 5.12. or if the matter require more haſte, a Lyon to teare him quickly, <hi>verſe</hi> 14. alſo to the houſe of <hi>Iudah,</hi> rottennes, which comes by degrees, <hi>verſe</hi> 12. or if more ſpeede muſt bee vſed, a Lyons whelpe that makes quick worke, goes away with the ſpiole, and none can reſcue it, <hi>verſe</hi> 14. In the booke of the <hi>Iudges;</hi> firſt, God kindles the fire of his wrath, ſelling his people (their ſin is the price) into the hands of a ſtrange Lord, but eight yeeres, <hi>Iudg.</hi> 3.8. after, hee makes the fire greater; and they ſerued <hi>Eglon</hi> (King of <hi>Moah</hi>) eighteene yeeres, <hi>verſe</hi> 14. and after; and laſtly, the fire was great indeed; for, he deliuered them into the hands of the Philiſtims 40. yeeres, <hi>Iudg.</hi> 13.1.</p>
               <p>An inſtruction to Chriſtians,<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> when they feele ſorrow after ſorrow, one croſſe after another, a greater after a leſſer, to lay all vpon their owne intractableneſſe vnder Gods gentler hand: for, what maruell where we renew our ſins that God ſhould renew his Plagues: &amp; where we vye, there he ſhould reuy, and come ouer vs with the ſame hand? that he ſhould puniſh with increaſe, where we increaſe the ſinne? and fetch his blowes often, when
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:17070:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>wee often ſinne againſt him? yet (as one ſaith) there is great difference betweene Gods children, and no chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, in this manner of dealing: for, Gods children, are firſt called by the Word: if that doe nothing, or little, they ſhall be called by ſome workes of his iuſtice in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: or, if they profit not that way, they ſhall feele ſmart themſelues; firſt, by light croſſes and ſeldome, and after by ſharper, and more often: and, if yet they abide in ſin, they ſhall be fetcht out, as out of the fire with ſtrong and long afflictions: but for ſuch as are no children but baſtards, they muſt look for one breaking after another till their necks be broken: Plague ſhall follow Plague, till the laſt be executed, as vpon <hi>Pharaoh.</hi> God will deale with them as wiſe fathers doe with graceleſſe children: he wil lay away the rod, and put them out of dores. And here, let vs (the people of this Kingdome) take heed: the Plague hath beene among vs, and hot in <hi>London:</hi> if ſo many warnings will not ſerue, what ſhall we looke for, but that God ſhould lay away the rod of our correction, ſaying; wherefore ſhould yee be ſmitten any more, <hi>Eſay</hi> 1.5. and ſo put vs out of the dores of his kingdome for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer? if the fire of Peſtilence cannot purge vs, there is a fire in hell will burne vs: ye that haue eſcaped out of the fire of Peſtilence, conſider; that yee goe not out of one fire, and another fire conſume you, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 15.7.</p>
               <p>An admonition to Chriſtians,<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> to pittie themſelues by amendment betimes: the longer they put off, the more they muſt ſuffer: and what wiſeman will not ſaue his skinne as much as he may? if he receaue one blow, he wil ward the ſecond, and arme againſt the third. Now, apply this to thy ſelfe: doth God lightly humble thee? that ſhould make thee, or ſhould not that make thee, when thou art vp againe, to looke better to thy waies,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:17070:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>and to thy feet to ſet them in Gods teſtimonies. O re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member this yee, that riſe from ſickneſſe to ſinne, not to amendment: hereby ye do but make worke for another, and ſmarter Viſitation. A man ſhould come out of ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, as gold out of the fornace, which is purer by it, &amp; more ſhining: but many come out worſe then they went in, who are not Gods gold but Satans droſſe: afflictions, ſicknes, pouerty, paine are the portions of ſin from God, and rods of nurture in the hands of a louing Father: but if the rod of nurture better vs not, rather if it make vs worſe, what hope of vs more then of <hi>Salomons</hi> foole, who being ſore and often beaten for his fault (it was of drunkenneſſe) would follow it yet more? <hi>Pro.</hi> 23.35. Of ſuch blockiſhnes and priuation of ſenſe we reade in the wicked <hi>Iſraelites;</hi> who though ſtrangers deuoured their ſtrength; and this was no ſmall affliction; yea, though gray haires were here and there vpon them, and this was no new affliction; yet they knew nothing, neither ſought the Lord for all this, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 7.9. no rod, no calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie could doe any good vpon them: were theſe wiſe for themſelues? or are they wiſe, that will fall a ſleepe in a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardles ſecurity, while they are in the heart of the ſea, and far from any ſhore, as did <hi>Salomons</hi> drunkard, who therefore might haue periſhed without all remedy? So for the careles and incorrigible in the hot brunt of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons</hi> laſt Mortality, what wiſdome in them, that they had no better regard; ſeeing that by ſuch ſenſleſneſſe of ſo fearefull and great a iudgement from God, they pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe more ſtrokes to the fooles backe, which cannot but bee ſo, when one ſtroke, and ſuch a one, can ſo little moue them, or neuer a whit?</p>
               <p>To haue thirty and eight yeeres ſickneſſe, and all that long time, to keepe in bed, muſt needs bee a grieuous
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:17070:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>chaine: yet Chriſt tells this Man of a worſe thing in chaines vnder darknes, binding to damnation: for ſuch a matter I take this worſe thing to be.<note place="margin">Doct.</note> And then we learn hence, that corporall paines here, ſhould breed care in vs to preuent eternall in the helles: for, therefore the Lord iudgeth vs here, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.32. and therefore, when we ſuffer here, &amp; but for a very ſhort time, (or rather no time, compared to time endles,) in the ache of a tooth or anguiſh of other member; and yet crie out as if we ſuffered, or ſhould ſuffer eternally: how ſhould this put vs in remembrance &amp; feare of that place where, &amp; thoſe torments wherein the wicked and all that forget God, doe, and muſt ſuffer world without end in euer burning flames of hell? ſhould not ſuch an occaſion ſet ſpurres of care into vs to auoid the worſe thing, when the thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was ſo grieuous and tormenting: the reaſons:<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſons </seg>
                  </label>
               </p>
               <p>Good reaſon it ſhould be ſo; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> for otherwiſe GOD ſhould looſe that labour, and we our ſoules. Secondly,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> then is the fitteſt ſeaſon: for, when can a man ſo fitly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member a ſmart, as when he ſmarts? and when ſo well minde the torments of hell, as when, by reaſon of tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments like thoſe, he can at no hand, minde and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber with pleaſure the pleaſures of ſin that bring downe to hell?</p>
               <p>A reproofe of thoſe who minde nothing in ſickneſſe but health; nor in priſon but liberty; <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>
                  </label> nor in paine but eaſe. They neuer labour, with bodily health to get ſauing health; nor with liberty from priſon, the liberty of Sons; nor with the eaſe of the fleſh, eaſe and reſt from their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours in another world: their happineſſe ſtands (all of it) in their riches, their life in their abundance, and their reioycings in the fauour of men: all their care is, not to preuent miſery for hereafter, but to ſtore themſelues
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:17070:20"/>with ſome fooliſh happines now: where <hi>Dauid</hi> yet in the higheſt flote of his kindomes, felt his ſins as a moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, &amp; the pardon of them, as the greateſt eaſe worldly, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32.1.2. to be ſhut vp in ſin, hee eſteemed it greater thraldome, then to be ſhut vp in priſon: and the fauour of God he deſired aboue all fauours here, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4.6. This vſe he made of his ſicknes cauſed by his ſin; the paine of it put him in minde of worſe paines, and more intollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, which was his benefit thereby for our imitation. I pray God the like mind may be found in thoſe, whether rich or poore, at whoſe hearts the Lord knocked by this laſt calamitie of Peſtilence; and I pray God it may bee found in all of vs to our amendments: <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>ECCLESIAST. 7.13.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Conſider the Worke of God.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
